<?xml version='1.0'?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"/usr/share/sgml/docbook/dtd/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" 
[
<!ENTITY cvs         "<acronym>CVS</acronym>">
<!ENTITY orocos      "<acronym>Orocos</acronym>">
<!ENTITY rtai        "<acronym>RTAI</acronym>">
<!ENTITY rtos        "<acronym>RTOS</acronym>">
]
>

<article>
 <articleinfo>
    <title>
      Introduction for Orocos developers
    </title>
    <subtitle><emphasis>Open RObot COntrol Software</emphasis>
    </subtitle>
    <copyright>
      <year>2006</year>
      <holder>Herman Bruyninckx, Peter Soetens</holder>
    </copyright>

    <abstract>
      <para>
	This document explains the goals, vision, design, implementation and
	packages of 
	<ulink url="http://www.orocos.org">&orocos;</ulink>,
	the <emphasis>Open RObot COntrol Software</emphasis> project. 
      </para>
    </abstract>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>0.22.0</revnumber>
	<date>10 March 2006</date>
	<authorinitials>ps</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Created from Orocos Overview document</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>
	Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
	under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or
	any later version published by the Free Software Foundation, with no
	Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover
	Texts. A copy of this license can be found at
	<ulink
	  url="http://www.fsf.org/copyleft/fdl.html">http://www.fsf.org/copyleft/fdl.html</ulink>.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>

  </articleinfo>
  <sect1 id="vision">
    <title>Development Vision</title>
    <para>
      Developing code for the Orocos project is guided by
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Software engineering requirements.</emphasis>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    What quality and approach are expected from contributions
	    to the project?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Structure of the source code.</emphasis>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    How is the project structured into sub-projects?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist> The project maintainers will <emphasis>strictly
	impose</emphasis> adherence to the project's vision and
      roadmap when considering incorporation of contributions to the
      project. However, they always welcome a motivated discussion
      about these topics on the project's <ulink
	url="http://lists.mech.kuleuven.be/mailman/listinfo/orocos">
	mailinglist. </ulink>
    </para>
    <sect2 id="proj-dev-req">
      <title>Software engineering requirements</title>
      <para>
	&orocos; has a vision on <emphasis>how</emphasis> developers should
	design, implement and present new functionality, in order to guarantee
	the project's coherence and scalability. These are the software
	engineering guidelines that support the implementation of the
	project's vision:
	<orderedlist>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Object-oriented design.</emphasis>
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      This seems an obvious requirement for modern-day software development.
	      However, the experience within the project has learned that designing
	      an appropriate class hierarchy is a <emphasis>major</emphasis>
	      challenge, mainly because of the diversity of the field.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Extreme decoupling and modularity.</emphasis>
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      This is the fundamental criterium to keep in mind when designing
	      and/or refactoring the project's class hierarchy.
	      Object classes encapsulate data and activities, and the choice of
	      classes should be such that:
	      <itemizedlist>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The implementation of one class should not rely on knowing something
		    about the internals of another class. Relying on such knowledge is
		    called <emphasis>coupling</emphasis> between both classes, and this
		    must be avoided at all costs, because it prevents the independent
		    evolution or re-implementation of the classes.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Every class should have an interface that fits more or less on one
		    single page. Elaborate interfaces are a sign that the implemented
		    functionality may better be split into multiple objects.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

	      </itemizedlist>
	      The strong desire to <emphasis>decouple</emphasis> software parts
	      wherever possible is a key feature of the project; it may seem a bit
	      of an overkill for each individual application built with the &orocos;
	      code (and hence a burden for the individual contributor), but for the
	      whole project it is expected to become its major competitive advantage.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Small and shallow interfaces.</emphasis>
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      It is useful to separate the <emphasis>interface</emphasis> of a
	      certain functionality from its <emphasis>implementation</emphasis> (as
	      a class or as a component). The interfaces are what Application
	      Builders and End Users need to construct their programs; the
	      class and component implementations are contructed by the Framework and
	      Component Builders.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Separated interfaces give more flexibility in changing
	      implementations, and in allowing &ldquo;third-party&rdquo; providers
	      of components. They also allow to discuss functionality without being
	      biased by possible implementations problems or opportunities.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      &orocos; prefers interfaces that are:
	      <itemizedlist>

		<listitem>
		  <para><emphasis>Small.</emphasis>
		    This improves the focus of the interface, and hence (hopefully) its
		    quality. In this sense, it corresponds to the minimality requirement
		    discussed below.  Another motivation is that &orocos; wants to avoid
		    &ldquo;exceptions&rdquo; in implementations of the interfaces: when
		    the interface is large, the chance increases that a particular
		    developer will not be able to provide a <emphasis>complete</emphasis>
		    implementation. In that case, the implementation must return an
		    exception &ldquo;functionality not implemented&rdquo;, and this
		    complicates the execution logic of the component that uses the
		    interface, and reduces the real-time performance.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para><emphasis>Shallow.</emphasis>
		    In an object-oriented paradigm, much functionality is provided by
		    class <emphasis>hierarchies</emphasis>. Every hierarchy may seem
		    natural in the context on one particular application, but it will most
		    certainly not be natural in other applications. For example, a
		    robotics engineer may find it normal to have a &ldquo;robot&rdquo;
		    object at the top of a large and deep hierarchy. But that same word
		    &ldquo;robot&rdquo; will not be well received by machine tool builders
		    that construct milling machines, or laser cutters. Although most of
		    the functionality of motion control and task execution will be the
		    same in both application areas. Therefore, class hierarchies should
		    not be deep.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

	      </itemizedlist>
	      In addition to the technical reasons to use small and shallow
	      interfaces, they are a key feature for free software projects that
	      expect significant contributions from their community: the complexity
	      of the whole system can only be tackled by restricting the scope of
	      each individual piece of code. An <emphasis>increased
		flexibility</emphasis> is a derived property that comes for free.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Distributable.</emphasis>
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Future machine control systems will most certainly use multiple
	      processors, connected through a network with sensors and actuators
	      that most probably will have their own embedded intelligence.
	      Hence, the robot/machine control software will have to be scalable and
	      distributable.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Having a design that is modular and maximally decoupled fulfills already
	      more than half of the requirements for such distributed control
	      systems. The other half will come from making software components
	      with an internal design that allows their different parts to cooperate
	      over a network.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Two software aspects are important in this respect: the ubiquitous use
	      of <emphasis>events</emphasis> for synchronization, and of a
	      <emphasis>virtual (network) time</emphasis> (instead of the time
	      delivered by the local processor). Both events and virtual time are
	      general <emphasis>abstractions</emphasis>, that are easily mapped on
	      corresponding primitives of the particular operating system the
	      component is running on. For example, a hardware interrupt is also an
	      event, and for the logic of a component it almost never matters
	      whether the event comes from the hardware or from a local
	      &ldquo;stub&rdquo; of remote hardware.
	      So, make sure that your components don't use system calls 
	      that tie them to a particular operating system or a particular device.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      &orocos; provides <emphasis>abstraction layers</emphasis> for both the
	      operating system and the interfacing hardware. These abstractions
	      follow the principles of minimality and decoupling. Especially for the
	      operating system abstraction this is a big advantage, because typical
	      (real-time) OSs tend to have way too large and too primitive APIs,
	      that are easily abused.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Minimalistic.</emphasis>
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Developers should only offer features that are
	      <emphasis>absolutely</emphasis> necessary: practical experience has
	      learned that the availability of superfluous APIs leads to
	      implementations with similar functionality but with different
	      implementations. And, worse, to implementations where the programmers
	      do not know very well what parts of the available functionality to
	      use.  Both effects lead to <emphasis>sub-optimal</emphasis> results,
	      and applications that are more difficult to re-use and maintain.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Platform independent.</emphasis>
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Because of its Free Software nature, Linux is the normal environment
	      for both host development and target runtimes. This can in practice
	      lead very quickly to an unperceived bias towards Linux, that would
	      compromise the portability to other operating systems. Developers must
	      try to use only portable language constructs.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Of course, sooner or later, the project will be confronted with the
	      trade-off between portability and the choice for a particular desired
	      feature that can not be supported by all initially targeted platforms.
	      These trade-offs must be discussed on the mailinglist.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Thorough large-scale design.</emphasis>
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Developers must <emphasis>always</emphasis> consider that their
	      designs will possibly be used in a very complex, distributed and hard
	      real-time implementation. Therefore, the design of such large-scale
	      robotics systems must be made clear before starting the implementation
	      of classes and components. And the implementators must provide
	      contributions that can safely and efficiently work in such
	      large-scale systems.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      One particular item is <emphasis>real-time</emphasis>: if an algorithm
	      <emphasis>is</emphasis> inherently real-time (i.e., it has a
	      deterministic execution time), then its implementation
	      <emphasis>must</emphasis> be implemented with constructs that are
	      real-time safe. For example, all variables and temporary objects must
	      be allocated before execution of the functionality proper, and no
	      exceptions or run-time type checking must be used. (So, Java
	      and C++ programmers need to be careful.)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	</orderedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	All these requirements illustrate the project's emphasis on
	<emphasis>design</emphasis>: most things in robotics have already been
	tried out in various ways, so the &orocos; implementation should
	<emphasis>at least</emphasis> be as good as the best of these
	tried-out predecessors. In addition, &orocos; aims at a number of
	extra features, such as &ldquo;ultimate generality&rdquo;.
	This generality is the reason why the project follows a development
	approach which is maybe a bit different from traditional free software
	projects: the trade-off during the current development is towards
	having a very well thought-out and very general design, and not in the
	first place towards adding as many functionality features as possible.
	This approach is motivated by the observation that all existing robot
	control software packages are very difficult to use in applications
	that are different from the first application they were built for. And
	that sharing source or binary code is very hard in practice, because
	of ill-defined interfaces, that are most often also strongly coupled
	to one particular application.
      </para>
      <para>
	The development approach of the project follows from the
	above-mentioned vision: the project works in a &ldquo;bottom-up&rdquo;
	fashion, on small interfaces at a time, <emphasis>but</emphasis> while
	keeping the long-term goal in mind. So, it is currently building the
	lowest levels of the framework, such as the hard real-time
	&ldquo;Core&rdquo;, motion control functionality, primitives for
	communication between &orocos; components, robot kinematics, etc.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <bibliography>
    <title>Bibliography</title>

    <biblioentry xreflabel="posa96">
      <title>Pattern-oriented software architecture: a system of
	patterns
      </title>
      <authorgroup>
	<author>
	  <firstname>Frank</firstname>
	  <surname>Buschmann</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>Regine</firstname>
	  <surname>Meunier</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>Hans</firstname>
	  <surname>Rohnert</surname>
	</author>
      </authorgroup>
      <pubdate>1996</pubdate>
      <publisher> <publishername>Wiley Chicester</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>

    <biblioentry xreflabel="gof94">
      <title>Design Patterns Elements of Reusable Object-Oriented
	Software
      </title>
      <authorgroup>
	<author>
	  <firstname>Erich</firstname>
	  <surname>Gamma</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>Richard</firstname>
	  <surname>Helm</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>Ralph</firstname>
	  <surname>Johnson</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>John</firstname>
	  <surname>Vlissides</surname>
	</author>
      </authorgroup>
      <pubdate>1994</pubdate>
      <publisher> <publishername>Addison Wesley</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>


    <biblioentry xreflabel="Johnson97">
      <biblioset relation="article">
	<title>Frameworks = (components + patterns)</title>
	<authorgroup>
	  <author>
	    <firstname>R. E.</firstname>
	    <surname>Johnson</surname>
	  </author>
	</authorgroup>
	<pagenums>39&ndash;42</pagenums>
	<volumenum>40</volumenum><issuenum>10</issuenum>
	<pubdate>1997</pubdate>
      </biblioset>
      <biblioset relation="journal">
	<title>Communications of the ACM</title>
      </biblioset>
    </biblioentry> 

    <biblioentry xreflabel="Szyperski98">
      <biblioset relation="book">
	<title>Component Software: Beyond Object-Oriented
	  Programming</title>
	<authorgroup>
	  <author>
	    <firstname>C,</firstname>
	    <surname>Szyperski</surname>
	  </author>
	</authorgroup>
	<publisher>
	  <publishername>Addison Wesley</publishername>
	</publisher>
	<pubdate>1998</pubdate>
      </biblioset>
    </biblioentry> 
  </bibliography>
</article>
