<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY orocos      "<acronym>Orocos</acronym>">
<!ENTITY oldversion  "2.5">
<!ENTITY version     "2.6">
]
>

<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>
      &orocos; Toolchain &version; Release Series
      Changes, New Features, and Fixes 
    </title>
    <subtitle>
			<emphasis>Open RObot COntrol Software</emphasis>
    </subtitle>
  </articleinfo>
  <para>
    This document provides a quick overview of what changed between
    the &orocos; Toolchain &oldversion; and version &version;.
  </para>
  <section id="upgrading">
    <title>Upgrading from RTT 1.x to Toolchain 2.x</title>
		<para>
			Please consult the online wiki for all available information about the 1.x to 2.x transition:
			<ulink url="http://www.orocos.org/wiki/rtt/rtt-20">The Road to RTT 2.0</ulink>.  The
			Real-Time Toolkit is no longer released as a single entity, but as part of a complete set of
			tools and libraries for creating real-time applications.  See also the changes documents of
			the previous major releases:
		 <itemizedlist>
			 <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.orocos.org/stable/documentation/rtt/v2.0.x/doc-xml/orocos-rtt-changes.html">Toolchain 2.0 Changes</ulink></para></listitem>
			 <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.orocos.org/stable/documentation/rtt/v2.1.x/doc-xml/orocos-rtt-changes.html">Toolchain 2.1 Changes</ulink></para></listitem>
			 <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.orocos.org/stable/documentation/rtt/v2.2.x/doc-xml/orocos-rtt-changes.html">Toolchain 2.2 Changes</ulink></para></listitem>
			 <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.orocos.org/stable/documentation/rtt/v2.3.x/doc-xml/orocos-rtt-changes.html">Toolchain 2.3 Changes</ulink></para></listitem>
			 <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.orocos.org/stable/documentation/rtt/v2.4.x/doc-xml/orocos-rtt-changes.html">Toolchain 2.4 Changes</ulink></para></listitem>
			 <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.orocos.org/stable/documentation/rtt/v2.5.x/doc-xml/orocos-rtt-changes.html">Toolchain 2.5 Changes</ulink></para></listitem>
		 </itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>
  <section id="caveats">
    <title>Important Caveats</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
				<para>
					This release is binary incompatible with RTT &oldversion;.x. You need to recompile the
					whole toolchain and all your applications in order to use this release.
				</para>
				<note><para> <emphasis>Take care that all previously built components and plugins in the
				&lt;install&gt;/lib/orocos directory and subdirectories are removed, since the component
				and plugin loaders may get confused if older versions are found.</emphasis>
				</para></note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
				<para>
					There was an API change in the (RTT internal) <classname>RTT::types::TypeInfo</classname>
					class. If you inherited directly or indirectly from this class, you'll probably need to
					inherit from <classname>RTT::types::TypeInfoGenerator</classname> instead and fabricate a
					<function>installTypeInfoObject()</function> function. There is generally no change needed on your
					side if you inherited from <classname>RTT::types::TemplateTypeInfo</classname>,
					<classname>RTT::types::StructTypeInfo</classname> or similar classes, since these classes
					have implemented <function>installTypeInfoObject()</function> function for you and inherit
					from <classname>RTT::types::TypeInfoGenerator</classname>.
				</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
				<para>
					There was an API change in the (RTT internal)
					<classname>RTT::marsh::PropertyLoader</classname> class. It requires now a TaskContext or
					Service in the constructor and no longer as argument to the rest of the API.
				</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>We no longer load component libraries with the RTLD_GLOBAL flag.</emphasis>
					This means you must link
					with all required libraries at link time, and not rely on symbol resolution during the
					loading by the deployer.
				</para>
      </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="ros">
    <title>ROS Users</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
				<para> The Orocos Toolchain 2.6.x will only be released in ROS Fuerte and later.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					We fixed issues of conflicting typekits (see more on that below). This means that its
					allowed now to load typekits from ROS and non-ROS packages, describing the same
					structs.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
  <section>
    <title>Improvements</title>
    <section>
      <title>Building</title>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Autoproj updates</emphasis>
					This release includes the latest Autoproj version and consequently features in
					order to manage your build process and code repository versions.
				</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>ROS_ROOT is no longer influencing your build, unless you're in a ROS_PACKAGE_PATH</emphasis>
					The last cornercases of ROS_ROOT influencing our build behavior have been ironed out in this release
				</para>
				<para>
					This fixes integration with AutoProj.
				</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>RTT and OCL builds with clang++ 3.0</emphasis>
					This allows you to speed up RTT builds significantly.
				</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>It's now possible to create applications that setup a CORBA proxy, without
					linking to TAO/OMNIORB directly, but only to the RTT corba transport.</emphasis> See the
					<classname>RTT::corba::TaskContextFactory</classname> class.
				</para>
      </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>TaskContext and Services</title>
      <itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis> A new connection type has been introduced, BUFFER_CIRCULAR.</emphasis>
						This new type can be used in the ConnPolicy.type field in order to have circular
						buffers instead of the classical non-circular buffer.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Exceptions thrown in operations are now detected and handled.</emphasis> When
						an operation threw an exception, this resulted in undefined behavior. The exception is
						now caught by RTT and the caller side receives an std::runtime_exception exception.
						Passing exceptions is not supported, so this is a last-resort solution to cope with
						misbehaving operations.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>The ComponentLoader is from now on part of RTT instead of OCL.</emphasis>
						This means you no longer need a DeploymentComponent to import typekits or component
						packages.
					</para>
				</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Data Types, Toolkits and Typekits</title>
      <itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>We restructured typekits such that it is now allowed to load multiple typekits for the same type.</emphasis></para>
					<para>
						If these typekits name the type differently, the names will function as an alias. Also,
						TypeInfo object pointers are now constant and can no longer become invalid in a running
						application.  The restructuring allows one to install a TypeInfo object and later-on
						add features such as type decomposition or transports. The classical TypeInfo subclasses
						all have been adapted, but if you created your own TypeInfo variant, you will need to
						update your code minimally.
					</para>
					<para>
						See the Caveats section above in case you wrote a custom typekit.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>The internal function getMember is now much more efficient and faster.</emphasis> There's now also
						a real-time version of getMember, if you provide it a ReferenceDataSource such that a
						reference to the member can be given without allocating a DataSource for it.
					</para>
				</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Operating Systems</title>
      <itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Creating a Linux thread now prints the TID or PID instead of the POSIX id, such that
						RTT threads can be correlated to normal Unix tools such as top or ps.
					</para>
				</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Orocos Component Library (OCL)</title>
		<section>
			<title>Lua scripting</title>
			<itemizedlist>      
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Consult the  <ulink
						url="http://www.orocos.org/wiki/orocos/toolchain/orocostoolchainluacookbook">LuaCookbook</ulink>
						for the latest changes
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
    <section>
      <title>Reporting</title>
      <itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The reporting component has been rewritten (again) boosting its performance sometimes a
						1000-fold (but at least a 100-fold), especially when using the NetCDF reporting component. We can now reliably log
						a dozen ports at 1kHz, using only 10% cpu on an Intel i7 system.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
	</section>
	<appendix>
		<title>About Orocos</title>
		<para>
			Please send your Orocos questions to <ulink
			url="mailto: orocos-users at lists.mech.kuleuven.be">
			orocos-users at lists.mech.kuleuven.be </ulink>. 
		</para>
		<para>
			These pages are maintained by <ulink
			url="http://www.orocos.org/orocos/whatis">the Orocos
			team</ulink>.
		</para>
		<para>
			For questions related to the use of the Orocos Software, please consult these
			web pages and the <ulink
			url="http://www.orocos.org/rtt">Orocos RTT manuals</ulink>. If
			that fails, the  <ulink
			url="mailto:orocos-dev at lists.mech.kuleuven.be">
			orocos-dev at lists.mech.kuleuven.be </ulink> mailing list might help.
			Please
			send comments on these web pages and the development of Orocos to
			our developer mailing list at  <ulink
			url="mailto:orocos-dev at lists.mech.kuleuven.be">
			orocos-dev at lists.mech.kuleuven.be </ulink>. All of
			our lists have <ulink url="http://lists.mech.kuleuven.be/mailman/listinfo/orocos-users">public
			archives</ulink> ( <ulink url="http://lists.mech.kuleuven.be/mailman/listinfo/orocos-dev"> dev public
			archive</ulink> ) .
		</para>
		<para>
			Copyright (C) The SourceWorks
		</para>
		<para>
			Verbatim copying and distribution of this entire article is
			permitted in any medium, provided this notice is preserved.
		</para>
	</appendix>
</article>
